Okay,
בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Yeah. Okay,
so today's פרק perek is today's דף daf is מ"ג, Mem Gimmel,
forty-three. We start a new פרק, perek, מומים אלו, Mumim Ellu, from
כל אלו מומים Kol Ellu Mumim to מומים אלו. Mumim Ellu. But
now we move from blemishes of animals to בכור bechor because to
בכורות bechoros to כהנים kohanim because we're like it's in the same
discussion although it's not strictly about בכור bechor unless someone wants to
talk about the fact about how כהנים kohanim replaced the בכורות, bechoros,
but that's not really the point. The point is the issue of
blemishes. So let's take a look.
We've had already a couple of references to this and how the
standards might be different and that's exactly what our פרק perek begins
with front and center.
So this is not in my you know where exactly.
מומים אלו
בין קבועין בין עוברין,
Mumim
ellu
bein kevu'in bein overin, these מומים mumim that we mentioned above, whether
they are fixed or transitory, right? If it's transitory by בכור, bechor,
you can't bring it as a קרבן, korban, but you also can't
שחט shecht outside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Either way, פוסלין באדם,
poslin ba'adam, they invalidate a כהן kohen for service because that at
least is conceptually similar. Even if it has a מום עובר, mum
over, a transitory blemish, you can't bring it as a קרבן korban
right now. So similarly if a כהן kohen has a מום עובר,
mum over, he can't serve in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So
conceptually that's similar. But now we move, ויתר עליהם, veyaser aleihem, and
but we have the following which are additional, which are present by
כהנים kohanim and not present by קרבנות. korbanos. הכיליון והלפתן, hakilyon vehaliftan,
so I will tell you what the גמרא Gemara says this means.
כיליון kilyon probably from the word כילוי kilui like to end or
to come to a to come to a like a point. Anyway,
כיליון kilyon is a pointy head, somebody that basically has a triangular
head and the top of it is pointy. לפתן liftan is turnip
head. It's like a great insult. Which is
well we'll get to something like that, which is basically wide at
the top and pointy at the bottom. המקבן, hamakban, you see we
have the המכבים haMaccabees here, I'm serious, המקבן hamakban is hammerhead.
So somebody, one explanation of that is is that the skull is
very large and the neck is very thin and it really looks
like you know like a hammerhead shark essentially, like protruding a long
protruding head in front and back. ושראשו שקוט vesherosho shakut is head
is שקוט, shakut, we'll see what this means in the גמרא. Gemara.
It could mean slanted, it could mean that his head sort of
is like he has a very short neck and it looks like
it's basically you know buried between his shoulders, depressed.
וסיקפת vesikfat and that the גמרא Gemara explains means that the back
of his head, it's not really rounded in the back, it's really
like sort of let's say flat like as if the back was
cut off. ובעלי
חטטרות uva'alei chatatarot and and people with a חטטרת chatateret which we
are going to see basically means certain types of nose issues.
I'm sorry, I just just escaped me for one second what exactly
the גמרא Gemara said that meant. Oh
I'm sorry, not nose, that's a different thing, excuse me, that's coming
later. No, it means like it means a hunchback, people with a
that cause because like with a big a big you know hump
in the back. Humpback, humpback or hunchback, it's the same, right? Hunchback.
And a חטטרת chatateret is
like yeah, I think because a חטטרת, chatateret, I think that's what
they call the hump of a camel also is a חטטרת. chatateret.
How much did they appear before the people, the כהנים kohanim in
the עבודה? avodah?
Well, I mean, they could first of all be ברכת כהנים Birkas
Kohanim but also when they brought your קרבן, korban, you know the
כהנים kohanim were running around and you were in the עזרה Azarah
presenting your קרבן. korban.
So they these this also פוסל posels them from ברכת כהנים? Birkas
Kohanim?
Well, nowadays we'll talk about nowadays. Nowadays it has to do right
now we're talking it's not clear. Let's so let's hold off. I
nowadays it's coming up and the relevance to ברכת כהנים Birkas Kohanim
although that's I think discussed a little bit more elsewhere but I'll
get back to you on that. Okay? Nowadays it really has to
do much more with things that are highly distracting visually to people
than the formal definition of מומים, mumim, but I need to double
check on that.
We're not even supposed to watch them anyway.
Right. Right, well that's true, exactly. Let me you know what, let
me get back to you on that. רבי יהודה מכשיר, Rabbi Yehuda
machshir, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that the hunchback is okay. חכמים
פוסלין. Chachamim poslin. Yes, presumably just on that.
חכמים פוסלין, Chachamim poslin, the חכמים Chachamim invalidate,
which is pretty much what we just said before.
Right. Not really. הכיריח, hakeirei'ach, bald,
פסול, pasul, invalid. Yeah. Now, the גמרא Gemara is going to limit
that to only certain types of baldness which are very unusual. איזהו
כיריח, eizehu keirei'ach, what is bald? כל שאין לו שיטה של שיער
מוקפת מאוזן לאוזן. kol she'ein lo shita shel sei'ar mukefet me'ozen l'ozen.
If you don't have one row of hair that goes all the
way around from ear to ear. The גמרא Gemara will discuss if
it means the entire circumference or around the front or around the
back.
Meaning you're completely bald.
Completely bald, although we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara, not we'll the
גמרא Gemara will deal with a couple of different possibilities. אם יש
לו הרי זה כשר, im yesh lo harei zeh kasher, if he
has, he's כשר. kasher. Now, right, now this is of course you
know challenging because
it's things that are... A mean they're not normal in the sense
that they're not in the center of your distribution graph, but they're
not exactly what you would call blemishes, you know, they're within the
range of the diversity of people.
And this is very common back then.
What? Certainly baldness, we'll see in the גמרא Gemara how it deals
with the baldness. Exactly. So we will take a look in the
גמרא Gemara and the גמרא Gemara will actually, you know, conceptually explain
that these are not actually מומים, mumim, they fall into a different
conceptual category. It still raises, you know, the challenging issue about what
does that mean that it's so important the visuals as opposed to,
you know, as defining who qualifies, but at least the גמרא Gemara
will say that these are not מומים, mumim, which is why they
only apply to כהנים kohanim and not to animals. Let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara.
Are אלו מומים? elu mumim?
I know, but nevertheless we'll see how the גמרא Gemara conceptually defines
it.
Quick, quick comment, it's interesting because the כהנים kohanim they all wore
a מצנפת, mitznefet, so were you able to really see the shape
of their head too well anyway?
Right, and like a lot of these things also would be, right,
which is also and and a lot of these things would be
covered by their clothes. Their clothes would cover most of them, you
know. How much? So it's not really about... we will see later
about a discussion about visuals, that visuals themselves are a problem but
they're a separate problem. But this is actually considered to be not
because of how it will distract the people, but just an intrinsic
problem, which heightens the concern because, you know, what I said yesterday
that the way I'm able to come to terms with it is
that, you know, that that even if obviously a person's worth is
not defined by this and this should not be a basis of
inclusion/exclusion but there has to be a
certain concession to human nature and how we, for us the aesthetics
are very important for a lot of people in a place of
worship but you see it by the whole way the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash is constructed. But if that were the issue then it
would only be these things that were in visible locations, which is
what, you know, Michael says. The fact that they're not limited to
that, you know, does, you know, does create an issue. Although I
should say most of the things that are mentioned here, shape of
the heads and the hunchback and baldness are all visual things. So
as we continue, yeah, well but still maybe visual somewhat. That's an
interesting question. As we continue, let's continue to see because I haven't
looked through it with an eye to that. Let's continue to see
whether it's limited to just visual things or even non-visible things. I
mean by non-visible I don't mean that they like we said before
that it's hidden inside the recesses of the body, but non-visible in
the sense that they would normally be covered up with clothing. So
let's take a look. I think that's a very interesting question. Let's
keep that in mind. Sholly, did you want to say something?
I was just going to say, aesthetics, I've davened in some really
ugly שטיבלס. shtiebels.
Right.
Well, I mentioned that the other day. For some people actually the
more humble the surroundings the better it is as a place for
דאוונען. davening. But you know, but for some people their sense of
like you know, a temple, means you know, all the gold and
the silver whatever, there's a certain sense of the place of God
and wanting the aesthetics to connect, you know, to be linked in
people's minds with what they would imagine would be with kings or
with nobility and so on. So there's a... so that you can
understand that it's connected to the whole aesthetics of the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. And it does not invalidate people not even the כהן
Kohen from receiving תרומה. terumah. It doesn't even invalidate him from sharing
in the קרבנות. korbanot. It only invalidates him from actually working. So
it is problematic I think, but nevertheless, you know, I think at
least you can understand it consistent with, you know, that that as
I said, like a concession to the human's need for a certain
aesthetics of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. But I think the question
of whether it would be visible or not is very important. So
let's keep that in mind. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
So the גמרא Gemara says אמאי, Amai, why is this true?
Now the why is this true is not yet on the differences,
but why is it true that there's of the things that are
the same, that everything that's invalid for a בכור bechor is invalid
for a
כהן. kohen. ויבלת דלא כתיבא באורייתא באדם. Veyabbelet delo ketiva be'Oraisa be'adam.
So now, if we were looking at the פסוקים, pesukim, which we
won't, but if you trust me here, Michael's going to go and
get a חומש, Chumash, then you would see that in אמור, Emor,
right, it has a whole list of, it says you know, כל
אשר יהיה מום בו לא תקריבו כי לא לרצון יהיה לכם יבלת
או שבור או גרב או או ילפת. Kol asher yihiyeh mum bo
lo takrivu ki lo leratzon yihiyeh lachem yabbelet o shavur o garav
o o yalafet. Anyway it has a whole list of specific מומים
mumim for בכור bechor of an animal, for not בכור, bechor, for
a קרבן korban of an animal, and then it has a whole
list of מומים mumim for כהנים. kohanim. There's a lot of overlap,
but there are some that are not overlapped. So the גמרא Gemara
is going to say, well if they're not completely overlapping what's listed
in the תורה, Torah, why should we assume that they equally apply
one to the other? Why don't we say each list is distinctive
for that category? היי יבלת, Hai yabbelet, so יבלת, yabbelet, which is
you know, what we sort of said, like it's a type of
a wart or a skin growth, דלא כתיבא באורייתא באדם, delo ketiva
be'Oraisa be'adam, is not mentioned under the מומים mumim in the תורה
Torah for man, for humans, for כהנים. kohanim. ותו, Vesu, and in
addition, דק ותבלול דלא כתיבא בבהמה, dak vesavlul delo ketiva beveheimah, how
about you know, the sort of mixed eye and the whatever it
was, the spots in the eye? Remember we had that in a
משנה mishna before, but that's not in the תורה Torah by animals.
That's only by humans. So how do you apply the things that
are mentioned by animals to humans and humans to animals? Maybe we
should say there are different lists. So the גמרא Gemara says, יליף
יליף מהדדי. yalif yalif mehadadi. No, you learn them one from the
other. דתניא detanya we taught in a ברייתא braita באדם לא נאמר
בו יבלת beadam lo ne'emar bo yavelet in by humans it doesn't
say יבלת yavelet ובבהמה לא נאמר דק תבלול uvevehema lo ne'emar dak
tavlul it never says this case about like the eye with the,
you know, the, the line going into the eye and mixing up
the white and the pupil. So מניין ליתן את האמור של זה
בזה ואת האמור של זה בזה? minayin liten et ha'amur shel ze
baze ve'et ha'amur shel ze baze? How do you know to
apply the one list to the other and vice versa? תלמוד לומר
talmud lomar גרב גרב יילפת יילפת לגזירה שווה garav garav yallefet yallefet
legezeira shava because by both of them it says או גרב או
יילפת o garav o yallefet it says which is, you know, which
is again these like type of a of a wart and scabs
and it says that both by humans and by animals. So that
allows you to make a גזירה שווה gezeira shava to apply one
list to the other.
So then it only is it only overlap of two things?
No, that I think there are more, but anyway we're making a
גזירה שווה gezeira shava there and you'll see why we do it
in a minute. And my goal, I'm going to predict that any
question you're about to ask is going to be asked here, so
let's see how the גמרא Gemara finishes asking all the questions and
then you'll tell me if you're left with any. Okay, so we
use those two to make a to link and to apply the
lists. So the גמרא Gemara says מופני. mufne. Now it has to
be thank you, it has to be it has to be free,
right? This is generally a principle. Which the גרב ויילפת? garav veyallefet?
Yes, that if you make a גזירה שווה gezeira shava with words
that are considered to be extra, then it means that don't ask
me any questions, my mind is made up, meaning don't ask me
any questions, I have a I have a link, this link allows
me to apply one to the other, there's no logic involved. You
can't ask me any logical questions. If the word is not extra,
then it's more of an analogy than it is a גזירה שווה.
gezeira shava. I'm only saying that loosely, but anyway it means that
it's subject to logical challenge. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is saying
these words have to be extra. דאי לא מופני de'i lo mufne
if they were not extra, איכא למיפרך ika lemifrach you could challenge
it in the following way and you could say the following: אדם
מבהמה לא יליף adam mibehema lo yalif you can't learn humans from
animals, maybe the list is maybe there's a bigger list by animal
or it's, you know, more things by animals. Why? שכן הוא עצמו
קרב לגבי מזבח. sheken hu atzmo karev legabei mizbe'ach. Maybe the aesthetics
matter more by animals because they're put on the מזבח mizbe'ach itself.
So there's a greater sense that it has to look perfect. Okay,
so maybe by animals maybe it's a bigger list and you can't
apply animals to humans.
Plus you don't cover up anything on an animal. You don't what?
Plus you can't cover up anything on an animal.
There you go, but we haven't even discussed that. Okay, so you
can't learn animals from humans.
בהמה מאדם לא יילף behema me'adam lo yalaf you couldn't have learned
humans from excuse me, you can't
learn humans from animals and now and you can't learn animals from
humans. Why? שכן נתרבה במצוות. sheken nitraba bemitzvot. A human has more
מצוות. mitzvot. Has מצוות, mitzvot, an animal does not. Now why does
that matter? So, you know, especially here by the כהן. kohen. It
really it does not make sense. What you what you would have
said is that maybe the one that's actually the subject and doing
the עבודה avoda and representing God or something, you know, maybe there's
a different standard, but that's not what the גמרא Gemara says and
the way רש"י Rashi explains it, it's really going to be a
phrase in the גמרא Gemara later is קדושתו מרובה kedushato meruba that
the intrinsic sense of קדושה kedusha that we have. So the animal's
קדושה kedusha comes from it's sanctified and it's designated, yes, but human
beings have a קדושה kedusha that they've been sort of, you know,
naturally sanctified to do מצוות. mitzvot. And that gives a but the
horse is naturally sanctified. I know, the funny thing is that our
normal קדושה kedusha to do מצוות mitzvot is not something to which
the concept of aesthetics or מומים mumim are at all relevant. It
actually that heightens the problem that we've been talking about, right? Because
it brings right, but it's one thing if you wanted to say
that a מום mum was a particular thing, it was נקרב על
גבי מזבח, nikrav al gabei mizbe'ach, it makes total sense. Why here
do we have a whole new category of aesthetics and מום? mum?
Because it's things that are done in the temple, they follow there's
a heightened concern of aesthetics. But to connect the idea of קדושה
kedusha of נתרבה במצוות, nitraba bemitzvot, you know, to me I just
find that very challenging because it brings the idea of the aesthetics
into not just the not just the world of the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, but into the well, holy and that holiness and מום
mum somehow are right, are at odds, right? And yeah, so that's
I I really do find that very challenging. If it weren't for
the later גמרא, Gemara, I could have said that נתרבה במצוות nitraba
bemitzvot just means sort of doing the מצוות mitzvot of the עבודה
avoda in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. But the גמרא Gemara later,
anyway maybe it's still possible to read it that way. Yes.
But the animals are also the object. Right, the כהן kohen is
just the means to do that offering. It's like a שוחט shochet
doesn't have to look perfect.
Right,
but on the other hand, we also call כהנים kohanim they're called
like like we call now, you know, the rabbis and whatever we
call them like, you know,
כלי קודש. klei kodesh. And the רמב"ם Rambam when he talks about
the הלכות halachot of כהנים kohanim talks about כלי המקדש והמשרתים בו
klei hamikdash vehamishartim bo and there are certain הלכות halachot that sort
of see the קדושת כהן kedushat kohen in similar ways like the
קדושה kedusha of the מנורה menorah and the מזבח, mizbe'ach, you know,
and the very fact like for example when we learn זבחים, Zevachim,
the feet of the כהן kohen have to have to be he
has to be barefoot, his feet have to touch the רצפה ritzpa
so that the קדושה kedusha he connects to the קדושה kedusha of
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So that's what I would have said,
meaning, you know, no, he's not like a שוחט, shochet, he's like
the מנורה, menorah, he's like the מזבח. mizbe'ach. is one of the
objects if you would in the temple and therefore the same way
those objects have to have a certain aesthetics, he has to have
a certain aesthetics. That to me is a more you know a
way that I can come to I can I you know you
know that I can explain this in a way that's sort of
that that that I find as religiously satisfying. But I'm not sure
how to fit that into נשרא במצוות, Nisra BaMitzvos, you know I
would have spoken about specifically the מצוות mitzvos of the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. Maybe that is what it means, but it doesn't sound
like that.
Like any other מצווה mitzvah that you're when you do a מצווה
mitzvah you're serving השם. Hashem.
Yes you are, but those don't connect to a concern of aesthetics,
right? And we don't somehow say that there's some sense of right
you know and so like again like I'm
doing a מצווה mitzvah I'm doing a...
Yes that's the מצווה mitzvah object, that's not the person,
right? No but I think we're all finding this challenging because you
don't want to sort of judge people based on their physical characteristics
and it would be troubling to think that that's the message of
the תורה. Torah. It's one thing to say it's part of a
particular aesthetics of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and the כהן kohen
as a כלי kli of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay
I understand. You're supposed to be certain ways when you're standing in
front of God but that's also the way of showing respect, that's
not a way that's something that you can control. It's not like
if you were born in a certain way with a certain deformity
oh you can't דאוון שמונה עשרה daven Shmoneh Esrei right because you
because you because you have a wart because you have a hunchback
so it's not appropriate for you to stand before God. We would
never חס ושלום chas v'shalom say such a thing
you know.
So what is what is this? This is more along the lines
of רש"י ביכורים Rashi Bikkurim whatever that is suggests that the greater
number of מצוות mitzvos referred to here are the מצוות mitzvos of
כהונה. kehuna.
Oh okay so there you go so that what I so ברוך
שכיוונתי baruch shekivanti okay so that's what I would have liked to
say. Okay so let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this so that that I think
is a nice way to explain this that it has to do
with it's the specific connection in the the specific context of the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this
okay לאיצטרוכי איצטריך l'aitztruchi aitztarich which one is extra? לכתוב רחמנא ילפת
ולא בעי גרב lichtov Rachmana yalefet v'lo ba'ei gerev because the תורה
Torah could have said ילפת yalefet which is and which is some
type of a skin you know whatever wart but I wanted גרב
gerev which is this very hard if you remember it said like
pottery like very dry more disgusting wart and I would have made
a קל וחומר kal v'chomer and I would have said where were
we
ולא בעי גרב ואנא אמינא v'lo ba'ei gerev v'ana amina I would
have said מה ילפת דלא מאיס הוי מומא mah yalefet d'lo ma'is
havei muma if this ילפת yalefet which is one type of a
skin wart is not is a blemish גרב דמאיס gerev d'ma'is גרב
gerev which is a very dry and disgusting one לא כל שכן
lo kol shekein it certainly is a
מום. mum. So why גרב דכתב רחמנא למה לי gerev d'chtav Rachmana
lama li why did it have to write גרב gerev in both
cases both by humans and by animals? I could have it's a
קל וחומר kal v'chomer from ילפת. yalefet. So לאתנויי l'atnuyei to make
it extra and by fact it's extra allows me to link and
apply one list to the next. ולכתבינהו רחמנא כולהו בחד v'lichtavinhu Rachmana
kulhu b'chad
now the גמרא Gemara is going to ask I would as I
was preparing the גמרא Gemara yesterday I said I bet Michael will
ask this but you see I told you to hold off so
I appreciate that. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute if you've
got a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah I've got a great idea. I'll
write the full list in one and only write the linking words
in another and you save yourself a lot of words and then
you can apply everything from one category to the next. See you
were going to ask that so thank you for showing some restraint.
ולכתבינהו רחמנא כולהו בחד v'lichtavinhu Rachmana kulhu b'chad why not write the
entire list in one of them וגרב וילפת הכא והכא v'gerev v'yalefet
hacha v'hacha and write the linking words גרב gerev and ילפת yalefet
in both places ולילפו מהדדי v'leilfu mehadadi
and learn them out from one another. Okay sometimes I switch the
text but whatever it doesn't matter. I know if you look at
the side מהדדי mehadadi it's better text. Okay so the גמרא Gemara
says אהיי ahei but by
which one do you want the תורה Torah to write the list
by? אי כתב באדם ei chtav b'adam if it were written by
humans הוי אמינא hava amina כל דפסול באדם פסול בבהמה. kol d'pasul
b'adam pasul b'beheimah. So fine I would have based on this link
apply everything from humans to animals but I would have had the
following problem.
קלוט וחלוט דליתנהו באדם kalut v'chalut d'leitnhu b'adam there are two מומים
mumim that are by animals that are not by humans. One is
קלוט kalut non-split hooves fused hooves. Okay you don't have that problem
by humans. We don't have fused hooves. Maybe maybe maybe but it
would be a different צורה tzura even if it were. So having
fused hooves is not by humans and חלוט chalut are the problems
about the roots of the teeth which are also not visible by
as visible by animals as they are by humans as they are
by animals. So those things the תורה Torah would not have couldn't
have applied by humans.
That's right they're way more visible.
They're more visible by animals. Animals open up their mouths wider when
they eat or bray or whatever. So דליתנהו באדם d'leitnhu b'adam so
בבהמה נמי ליפסלו b'beheimah nami lypseilu I wouldn't have been able to
apply them to animals because I would have just had the human
list and I wouldn't have had the things that are distinctive by
animals. All right try it the other way. לכתוב רחמנא כולהו בבהמה
lichtov Rachmana kulhu b'beheimah write the list by animals and then apply
them to humans. הוי אמינא hava amina כל דפסול בבהמה פסול באדם
kol d'pasul b'beheimah pasul b'adam fine everything that applies to animals applies
to humans. But
גיבן וחרום דליתנהו בבהמה giben v'charum d'leitnhu b'beheimah how about the גיבן
giben which is a problem with the eyebrow? We'll see it means
like one eyebrow or no eyebrows. Okay now animals don't have eyebrows.
Okay that so that would not have applied by animals. Or חרום,
charum, חרום charum is that the nose here, the ridge between your
eyes, is there's no ridge, like the nose is pressed in between
the eyes, the way the גמרא Gemara explains you can basically run
like an eye applicator, an eyeshadow applicator, from one eye to the
next and it won't hit any barrier in between. Okay, so that's
the ridge, that's the part of your nose that's between the eyes
is depressed. So that's not by animals because animals' noses are below
their eyes, so it's not an issue to begin with. So those
cases דליתנהו, d'leisnhu, where am I, דליתנהו בבהמה d'leisnhu b'veheimah don't aren't
don't exist by animals, באדם
נמי לא לכתבו b'adam nami lo lichtvu won't have applied by humans.
So therefore I can't apply the whole list one and just connect
it. So now of course the next obvious question Michael is going
to be, okay, thank you for your state, so have the distinctive
things in each category but the common things just in one list,
and then apply at least the common things. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says, see? I knew you'd figure out this whole גמרא, Gemara,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
okay, so the גמרא Gemara says לכתוב רחמנא כולהו בחד. lichtov rachamana
kulhu b'chad. So fine, write the whole list that's shared, the common
list, by only one of them. והנך דליתנהו, v'hanach d'leisnhu, the side
says באדם לכתוב באידך, b'adam lichtov b'idach, והנך דליתנהו בבהמה v'hanach d'leisnhu
b'veheimah or דליתנהו באידך לכתוב רחמנא בבהמה, d'leisnhu b'idach lichtov rachamana b'veheimah,
והנך דליתנהו באידך לכתוב באדם. v'hanach d'leisnhu b'idach lichtov b'adam. So the
ones that are distinctive that don't exist by animals, just write by
בהמה, beheimah, don't apply by בהמה, beheimah, just write by humans. And
but the common list does not have to be written twice. Why
was the common list written twice? וגרב וילפת הכתב הכא והכא v'gerav
v'yalefet hachtav hacha v'hacha and the words גרב gerav and ילפת yalefet
which allow for the link should be written in both places, וילפי
מהדדי v'yilfei mehadadi and write the and learn one from the other.
So instead write the distinctive ones in each list, the גרב gerav
and ילפת yalefet as the link, and the common ones write only
once. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא כדתני דבי רבי ישמעאל. ella
k'detani d'bei Rebbe Yishmael. The answer, it's funny why it says אלא
ella because this is really more or less in the same lines
of what it's been saying, the answer is what they teach in
the דבי רבי ישמעאל. d'bei Rebbe Yishmael. דתני דבי רבי ישמעאל, detani
d'bei Rebbe Yishmael, they teach in the house of רבי ישמעאל, Rebbe
Yishmael, כל פרשה שנאמרה ונשנית, kol parsha shene'emrah v'nishnis, any פרשה parsha
that was said once and repeated a second time, לא נשנית אלא
בשביל דבר שנתחדש בה. lo nishnis ella bishvil davar shenischadesh bah. You
don't have to justify the entire everything in that פרשה. parsha. If
it wanted to tell you one new thing then it nevertheless would
have gone over everything. A perfect example is why the list of
kosher and non-kosher animals is almost identical two times in the תורה
Torah but there are some slight differences: השסועה hashasuah and so on,
so the דאה, da'ah, the ראה, ra'ah, etc. So he says yeah,
this now of course this very much fits with the רבי ישמעאל
Rebbe Yishmael philosophy, not the רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva philosophy. רבי עקיבא
Rebbe Akiva wants to דרוש darosh every single letter, every single word.
רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Yishmael is much more דיברה תורה כלשון בני אדם.
dibra Torah k'lashon bnei adam. So fine, yes, technically you could have
just said one or two things that were distinctive, but once it
had to say the one or two that were distinctive by אדם
adam that weren't by בהמה, beheimah, it's going to give you a
more complete list and you don't need to justify why everything is
there. Yes, Charlie?
I've heard over and again there's not a single ו vav or
י yud that in the תורה Torah that isn't important. But there
are other places in the גמרא Gemara where they indicate.
So there is really two schools and that's why I said there's
the רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva school, that רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva was
דורש קוצי אותיות, doresh kotzei osiyos, you know, even the little, you
know, crowns on the letters. And there's רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Yishmael that's
of the school of דיברה תורה כלשון בני אדם. dibra Torah k'lashon
bnei adam. And that plays out in a lot of ways that
רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva learns out things like the famous example is
that רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Yishmael says to רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva, אפילו
אתה דורש בת ובת כל היום כולו איני שומע לך, afilu atah
doresh bas u'vas kol hayom kulo eini shomeia lach,
which is like even if you want to talk about extra ו
vavs the whole day and try to use it to prove something,
I'm not going to listen to you. Okay, so you know, so
רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Yishmael was not that, you know, this is an
approach called omnisignificance.
Okay, every single little thing is telling you something. Okay, that obviously
was something that obviously
kabbalistically, you know, very much the רמב"ן Ramban says at the beginning
of בראשית Bereishis that the entire תורה Torah is one big name
of God. And that's why, you know, from בראשית Bereishis at the
beginning of the ב של בראשית beis shel Bereishis to the ל
של כל ישראל, lamed shel kol Yisrael, you know, and there, I
mean, so obviously there's these approaches of every single letter is significant
and then there's more of a רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Yishmael approach of
דיברה כלשון בני אדם, dibra k'lashon bnei adam, and that plays out
in, you know, in many, in particularly in hermeneutics and in דרשות.
drashos. Okay.
And it's רבי ישמעאל'ס Rebbe Yishmael's ברייתא beraisa that we recite every
morning.
Well yes, although it's interesting we recite his ברייתא beraisa but his
ברייתא beraisa opens up the ספרא Sifra which is according to רבי
עקיבא. Rebbe Akiva. So why exactly we recite his ברייתא beraisa is
a little bit of a question. But you know, anyway, yeah. So
obviously רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Yishmael says, you know, we'll say presumably the,
you know, that obviously there's something that's being taught, but this actually
sounds like you don't even have to argue that. The תורה Torah
wanted to say one thing, you know, it'll say the whole פרשה
parsha and you shouldn't you shouldn't lose sleep overnight about why it
had to repeat all these extra פסוקים. psukim. You know, it certainly
helpful when you get to like a ויקהל Vayakhel פקודי Pekudei פרשה
parsha to approach it like a רבי ישמעאל. Rebbe Yishmael. Yes, Master
of הגשה עש"ק?
Hagashah E.S.K.? Oh that was נחום איש
גם זו.
Nachum
Ish Gam Zu.
Okay. Wasn't he, wasn't he a רבי rebbe of רבי עקיבא? Rebbe
Akiva? I'm thinking...
somebody could find out, Charlie could do a quick search for us
about נחום איש גם זו. Nachum Ish Gam Zu.
I think he might have been a רבי Rebbe of, I'm not
sure, that's a good question. But he gave it up at the
end, את ה' אלוהיך תירא פירש, et Hashem elokecha tira peireish, right?
So he stopped being דרשנינג.
darshening. But then someone said it.
What?
And רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, oh there you go, perfect. עקיבא Akiva
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva דרש, darash, את ה' אלוהיך לרבות תלמידי חכמים.
et Hashem elokecha l'rabot talmidei chachamim. So you see רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva took up the mantle that נחום איש גמזו Nachum Ish Gamzu
left. He said I can't דרשן darshen everything and רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, it works out perfectly. Okay, I think he might have been
a...
נחום איש גמזו Nachum Ish Gamzu has a Facebook page.
You'll tell me if he's a רבי Rebbe of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, but certainly I don't think that ever occurred to me in
exactly that way. Yes, he was רבי עקיבא's
Rabbi Akiva רבי's Rebbe teacher.
There you go, and that's exactly the point, he's picking up the
mantle. Okay, so now moving on. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, למה לי
דכתב רחמנא מום באדם מום בקדשים מום בבכור? lama li d'katav rachmana
mum b'adam, mum b'kodshim, mum b'bechor?
Now
there are three times it says מום. mum. By humans and by
קדשים, kodshim, which we now said you learn one from the other,
both in אמור, Emor, and by בכור bechor by דברים. Devarim. And
now as we've been, I was pointing out to you the entire
last פרק, perek, although the פרק perek opens by learning a generic
idea of בכור bechor as by בכור bechor of מום mum by
כל מום רע, kol mum ra, right? In the end, as you
continued in the פרק, perek, you saw drawing on categories that were
mentioned by other קדשים, kodshim, and one of the last משניות mishnayot
we learned basically said the same מומים mumim apply to בכור bechor
and to קדשים. kodshim. So in the end, we're really sort of
leveling all the categories and learning them from one another. So רבא
Rava says, so if you're learning them all from one another, why
did it have to be written all three times? Now he's not
asking the question before about, you know, the distinctive מומים, mumim, but
why for example did the תורה Torah have to just say, you
know, why did it have to say a מום mum is a
problem for example? Why not just say here are the מומים mumim
of animals, here are the מומים mumim of כהנים, kohanim, but the
fact that a מום mum is a problem, let me just infer
if it's a problem for one, it's a problem for the other.
So he's not talking about the specific מומים, mumim, he's that fine,
you know, like רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael and you need to write,
but why does the תורה Torah have to say that מום mum
was a problem? Couldn't I have inferred that it was problematic? Yeah.
So what we're trying to understand is, getting back to this list
of these two, is that so basically we're saying the reason why
you have to have more extensive, you don't have to be troubled
by the fact that there's a more extensive list because the תורה
Torah would do that to teach you specific things. But I still
don't understand, but there's still some things that apply to both. In
other words, if we're already going through effort to, like say more
than, I would say the whole thing, you know, within or or
not.
No, it's an abbreviated list.
Right, no, but then how do you, why does it pick these
things to mention and not those?
Alright, that's a, yeah, that's a question, but it's not a pressing
question, you know? It's not like, it's not like that there's, we
understand that in general the תורה Torah repeated what it liked to,
you know, to what's called an abbreviated list. You're not going to
just say oh here are the distinctive things. You want to give
a sense of what's in the whole category, but you don't have
to be exhaustive, that you can figure out later. It is very
much כלשון בני אדם, k'lashon bnei adam, right? You know, you know,
somebody will give like a list, you know, they'll say, you know,
we need to buy I don't know, you need to buy stuff
for the party, you know, cakes, you know, cakes, hats, whatever, everything
we got last time when we had a party, right? So you're
not going to just say everything we got, you'll give a couple
of examples and then you'll say and everything we got, you know,
etc., everything we got last time for the party.
But it's a bit unusual, what I'm saying, like it's not like,
you know, oh yeah you're going to the city center, you know,
I hear you saying like this מום mum but not that מום
mum and that מום mum and not the other.
I understand, we're giving a few examples. We need to get a
cake, we need to get a hat, we need to send out
invitations, just do everything we did last time. Okay, I think that's
very much כלשון בני אדם. k'lashon bnei adam. You give a short
list and then you don't have to make it exhaustive.
It's a category.
Alright, anyway, let's go on. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
So why did it have to say that מום mum was a
problem in all three places? We're now not talking about the specifics,
but the fact that it was a problem. So let's take a
look. למה
לי דכתב רחמנא מום באדם מום בקדשים מום בבכור? lama li d'katav
rachmana mum b'adam, mum b'kodshim, mum b'bechor? צריכא, Tsricha, you need it
in all cases. דאי כתב רחמנא מום באדם D'i katav rachmana mum
b'adam by people, כהנים, kohanim, שכן נתרבה במצוות, sheken nisraba b'mitzvot, that
maybe is distinctive because of the extra מצוות, mitzvot, which
we will happily take the explanation of whoever it was that was
what I would have liked to have said anyway, thank you ראשית
ביכורים, Reishis Bikkurim, that says that it means because of their particular
role as משרתים meshartim in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So therefore
there's a particular aesthetics maybe that would be distinctive by them. אדם
מבכור אדם
מבהמה לא אתי. Adam m'bechor, adam m'behema lo ati. Now you cannot
have learned an אדם adam from בהמה, behema, why not say oh
if a בהמה behema has a problem certainly an אדם adam that
is working in the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? No, שכן עצמה קרב
לגבי מזבח, sheken atzma karev legabei mizbeach, maybe there's a different aesthetics
and a higher aesthetics by animals that are put on the מזבח.
mizbeach. קדשים מבכור לא אתי. Kodshim m'bechor lo ati. Now why couldn't
you have learned that קדשים kodshim from בכור, bechor, right? If those
are both of those are put on the מזבח? mizbeach? So שכן
קדושתם מרחם. sheken kedushatam meirechem. בכור bechor has a higher קדושה kedusha
that it was born from the moment it was born, or a
certain type of a קדושה, kedusha, and therefore maybe the aesthetics and
the מומים mumim problem are bigger from there. So therefore what have
we now said? We
said that you cannot learn one minute, שכן... sheken... מום באדם שכן
נתרבה במצוות. mum b'adam sheken nisraba b'mitzvot. אדם מבכור בהמה לא אתי
שכן עצמה קרב לגבי מזבח. Adam m'bechor behema lo ati sheken atzma
karev legabei mizbeach. קדשים מבכור... Kodshim m'bechor... right. So humans cannot be
learned, humans and קדשים kodshim cannot be learned from בכור. bechor. בכור
bechor maybe has a higher demand because it's קדוש מרחם kadosh meirechem
and it's
אגבי מזבח. agabei mizbeach. לא אתי שכן הן עצמן קרבין *lo asi
sheken hein atzmon krevim*.
You can't learn humans from קדשים kodashim *kodashim* because the קדשים *kodashim*
are themselves put on the altar; maybe they have a higher aesthetics
than human. בכור bechor, מקדשים לא אתי *Bechor mikodashim lo asi*. Why
not learn בכור *bechor* from קדשים *kodashim*? If קדשים *kodashim* can't have
a מום mum. *mum*, certainly בכור *bechor* that is קדוש מרחם *kadosh
merachem*. שכן קדושתם מרובה *sheken kedushasam meruba*. It has a greater קדושה
*kedusha*. What does greater קדושה *kedusha* mean? So רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* says
it means that it applies to not only firstborns but to any
animal, not only males, even females. There's a lot of different types
of קדשים *kodashim*. It's a much bigger category. You could have also
said that a בכור *bechor* you can eat with its מום mum.
*mum* outside the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. You can't do it by
another קרבן *korban*. So there's a way in which the קדושה *kedusha*
of a בכור *bechor* is not as restrictive as the קדושה *kedusha*
of קרבנות *korbanos*. So basically you can't learn anything from humans. Humans
are distinctive, נתרבה במצוות *nisrabeh bamitzvos*. Maybe means like they actually, like
I said, serve in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. You can't learn
anything from בכור *bechor*. That's distinctive; it has קדושה מרחם *kedusha merachem*.
You can't learn anything from קדשים *kodashim*. It's אגבי מזבח *agabei mizbeach*
and also it is a broad category. So therefore cannot have just
said it from one. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this: חדא מחדא לא אתי *chada michada lo asi*. Fine, you can't
learn one from another. תיתי חדא מתרתי *Teisei chada mitartei*. Why not
learn one from two? Say it only by two of them. Why
say it in all three? מהאי תיתי *Mehai teisei*. From which two
do you want to learn out? לא ליכתוב רחמנא בבכור *Lo lichtov
rachmana be'bechor* and ותיתי מהנך *veteisei mehanach* and learn out from קדשים
*kodashim* and humans. If קדשים *kodashim* and humans a מום mum, *mum*
is a problem, certainly בכור *bechor* that is קדושה מרחם *kedusha merachem*.
Okay, and you know, so מה הנך שכן קדושתן מרובה *mah hanach
sheken kedushasan meruba*. No, because humans and and and non-בכור *bechor*, normal
קדשים *kodashim*, have greater קדושה *kedusha* than בכור *bechor*. What does it
mean? First of all, קדושתן מרובה *kedushasan meruba*, like we said before,
that at least by other קדשים *kodashim* it applies to a broader
category of things. And number two, as I said before, as I
would like to interpret this, not what רש"י *Rashi* said, that it
means that a non-בכור *bechor* cannot be eaten out of the בית
המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, a בכור *bechor* with a מום mum. *mum* can
be. So there's a higher קדושה *kedusha* by these things. ונוהגים בפשוטים
*venogim bipshutim*. And it doesn't end; it applies to all, all people,
not just to firstborns. So therefore they, maybe they have a higher
level. בכור *bechor* is a narrower category and maybe מום mum *mum*
would not be as problematic. לא ליכתוב בקדשים *Lo lichtov bekodashim* and
ותיתי מהנך *veteisei mehanach*. Learn out from humans and בכור *bechor*. מה
הנך שכן קדושתן מעליהם *mah hanach sheken kedushasan me'aleihem*. Humans and בכור
*bechor* are קדוש *kadosh* naturally. כהנים kohanim *kohanim* from being born and
בכור *bechor* from being born. So maybe that gives them a distinctive
level and demands a higher sense. לא ליכתוב באדם *Lo lichtov be'adam*
and ותיתי מהנך *veteisei mehanach*. How about not writing by humans and
learning out from בכור *bechor* and קרבנות *korbanos*? No, מה הנך שכן
הן עצמן קרבין לגבי מזבח *mah hanach sheken hein atzmon krevim legabei
mizbeach*. They're on the מזבח *mizbeach*. Maybe that demands a higher aesthetics.
צריכי *Tzrichi*, so you need all three. So again though, I would
like to say, and I very much appreciate the comment of the,
who was it? ראשית ביכורים *Reishis Bikurim*? ראשית ביכורים *Reishis Bikurim* that
says that even the נתרבה במצוות *nisrabeh bamitzvos* is very much in
the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* context. And that these concerns with appearances
and aesthetics or whatever, as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says about you
put it on the מזבח *mizbeach*, have very much to do with
the aesthetic demands of the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* and are not
supposed to be sort of, you know, which should not be generalized,
you know, very much are limited within that particular context. The question
about מומים mumim *mumim* that are naturally covered up is an interesting
question and we, let's keep that in mind as we continue. Right
now we're clearly only dealing with visible.
You mentioned במה *bama* a lot, so are you saying also the
time of במה *bama* you couldn't if you had a מום mum
*mum*?
No, that's an interesting question. I think you can. I'm trying to
remember, there is a discussion about that גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but that
wouldn't be a problem at all because the same aesthetics that are
demanded in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* are not demanded in your
local שול *shul*, right? It's a very, only in this one central
place is, you know, with all of the gold and all of
the silver and all of whatever, this has to have a particular
aesthetics which is important for, you know, most people. You know, the
one place which is supposed to be the, you know, the central
place of worship and particularly, you know, probably tapping into people's sense
of royalty and so on and all of that and all of
that beauty, you know, external beauty. But that's not necessarily, you know,
anything to be translated elsewhere, right? Nobody says you have to make
your בית כנסת *beis knesses* out of gold and silver.
So I will double check, that's a good point, and I'm pretty
much sure we פוסקין *pasken* that a בעל מום mum. *ba'al mum*
is not a problem on a במה *bama*. Okay, so let's take
a look.
But there are certain animals that you can't put on a במה
*bama* if it's missing a limb for instance.
All right, I meant, yeah, I meant בעל מום mum. *ba'al mum*
of humans. Oh, okay, okay. Right, the thing that's גוף עצמו קרב
*guf atzmo karev*, that might be different regardless. Okay,
but let me, let me look into that. I'll try to get
back to you about that tomorrow. Okay, יתר עליהם באדם *yeser aleihem
be'adam*. More
than
this is with humans. הני מילי *hani mili*. Now we're going to
get to the category that humans are even a broader category than
animals, even these things like shapes of the head and baldness. So
אמר רב יוחנן אמר קרא *amar Rav Yochanan amar kra*, and we
had this quoted a few days before in a couple of different
contexts, כל איש אשר בו מום mum, מזרע אהרן *kol ish asher
bo mum mizerah Aharon*, any man that has a blemish from the
seed of Aaron. you know, לא יקרב lo yikrav להקריב לחם אלוהיו.
Cannot draw close to bring the offerings. So we make the דרשה:
drasha: איש מזרע אהרן, Ish mizerah Aharon, איש ששוה בזרע של אהרן.
ish sheshaveh bezera shel Aharon. It's not only about being a blemish,
it's about looking like everyone else. Okay, which is pretty amazing, right?
That's exactly the types of things that, you know, like I said,
where we're supposed to sort of, you know, we think, you know,
embrace diversity, but it's very much about taking that narrow strip of
like the, you know, about what, you know, when you do that,
what is it, the bell-shaped curve, you know, only within like, you
know, one standard deviation. So here, even if it's not a blemish,
if it's not within that sort of one standard deviation within כל
זרע של אהרן, kol zera shel Aharon, it's a problem. Now, yeah,
maybe, I mean, we'll see in the גמרא Gemara how far this
goes.
I think if you're really tall, it's like a... right, or like
this nice...
right, it still raises questions, right, what types of things do you
evaluate that based on? Let's say a guy's particularly good-looking. Right.
So presumably it's still things that we consider to be somewhat, you
know, disturbing aesthetically, but it's still not something that we would consider
to be a מום. mum, So let's take a look at what
the גמרא Gemara says. And now the גמרא Gemara does say this
is not as bad as a מום. mum. מאי איכא בין מומא
לשאינו שוה בזרע של אהרן? Mai ika bein muma leshe'eino shaveh bezera
shel Aharon?
What's the difference about whether we call something a blemish or just
say it's not sort of like, you know, it's not within the
normal range of distribution? So the גמרא Gemara, says משום אחולי עבודה.
mishum achulei avoda. So it makes a very surprising statement. You never
would have thought this based on our משנה. Mishna. Our משנה Mishna
says these are additional מומים mumim, for humans, so you would have
assumed that these things, the hammerhead, the turnip head, whatever, is a
מום, mum. and that if the person does the עבודה, avoda, it's
פסול, pasul, like normally if you have a מום. mum, The גמרא
Gemara says no, this is a separate category. This is just that
it's not sort of within the normal range. And you're not allowed
to do it, but if you do it, it's not a מום
mum, and you did not invalidate the עבודה. avoda. מומא מחיל עבודה,
Muma machil avoda, a מום mum, invalidates עבודה, avoda, דכתיב, dechtiv, the
verse says, מום בו ולא יחלל. mum bo velo yechalel. If you
have a blemish, and therefore he shall not desecrate, he shall not
work because if he
does the עבודה, avoda, he'll desecrate. שאינו שוה בזרע של אהרן לא
מחיל עבודה. She'eino shaveh bezera shel Aharon lo machil avoda. Does not
desecrate the עבודה. avoda. It's just, you know, it says כל איש
מזרע אהרן kol ish mizerah Aharon is learned out, we're going to
see in a minute, actually even as an עשה aseh or whatever
it is, but it is not actually a לא תעשה lo ta'aseh
and it does not invalidate. So the גמרא Gemara, says מאי איכא
בין שאינו שוה בזרע של אהרן ומשום מראית העין? mai ika bein
she'eino shaveh bezera shel Aharon umishum marit ha'ayin? Now, מראית העין, marit
ha'ayin, we normally assume, what's that doing here? We normally mean, like,
you know, don't have your non-dairy creamer out with your after פליישיג
fleishig meal. But מראית העין marit ha'ayin means the way things appear
to the eye. And we're going to see in the next משנה
Mishna that there are things which are, which are just sort of,
for example, somebody's eyelashes fall out
would be an example. Fall out, his eyelashes. Okay. So that like
looks weird and it's distracting to people visually, but we're not going
to call it a מום. mum. Maybe it's natural enough, or they
say his teeth fall out, he's very old. So it's natural enough,
we're not going to call it a מום. mum It's not even
perhaps too much of a standard deviation. You know, maybe a lot
of people's teeth fall out. Okay,
so whatever, but for some reason we have to decide which falls
in which category. But it could be that we're saying either that
it's not a characteristic, you know, like Michael asked before, let's say
you're too tall. I mean, what types of things are even things
that we measure based on difference based on? That's one question, you
know, or it could just be that it is natural. It's not
a מום, mum, it's natural, but nevertheless it's very visually distracting, you
know, and that's more the issue by the way for ברכת כהנים.
birkat kohanim. We'll get back with more specific about and to it
tomorrow. So that's called מראית העין. marit ha'ayin. Not a מום, not
a problem of זרע של אהרן, zera shel Aharon, but nevertheless the
משנה's Mishna going to say it is a problem that it's visually
distracting. So what's the difference of those two? איכא בינייהו עשה. Ika
beineihu aseh.
That one is purely rabbinic, the visually distracting, that's not in the
Torah at all. The idea of אינו שוה בזרע של אהרן eino
shaveh bezera shel Aharon is biblical. There's a מצות עשה. mitzvot aseh.
What עשה? aseh? If you look at רש"י, he says, עובר בעשה
אם עבד. over be'aseh im avad. דהכי משמע, Dehachi mashma, the second
narrow line, השוה בזרע אהרן הוי כהן ויעבוד ושאינו השוה לא יעבוד.
hashaveh bezera Aharon havei kohen veya'avod veshe'eino hashaveh lo ya'avod.
So it's very strange what even עשה aseh we have. Actually the
פסוקים psukim are phrased in a לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. כל איש
מזרע אהרן אשר יהיה בו מום לא יקרב להקריב לחם אלוהיו. Kol
ish mizerah Aharon asher yihiyeh bo mum lo yikrav lehakriv lechem elohav.
But we have decided that the לא יקרב is only going on
the מום. And the fact that it's שוה בזרע של אהרן, shaveh
bezera shel Aharon, this normal distribution, that's only saying somehow an implicit
עשה. aseh. Only then is it appropriate for you to do the
עבודה. avoda. So actually the גמרא, Gemara so you know, with us
I think being a little bit grappling with this whole concept of
מומים, we should appreciate that the גמרא Gemara. radically reduced it, right?
We have all of these things at כהנים koanim that the משנה
Mishna calls, seems to call a מום. And now we said no,
no, no, no, that's just a problem of שוה בזרע של אהרן.
shaveh bezera shel Aharon. That's not a real מום, that's just not
standard deviation, and therefore it's only, it's not even a לא תעשה,
lo ta'aseh, it's not מחיל העבודה, mechal ha'avoda, it doesn't desecrate the
עבודה, avoda, it's only an עשה. aseh. And that's all it is.
And the things that are מראית העין marit ha'ayin that are visually
distracting, that clearly is only rabbinic, that's not even an עשה. aseh.
Okay, so those are the conceptual categories very nicely laid out by
the גמרא, Gemara together with also very nicely laying out that fundamentally
the specifics of the blemishes are basically the same whether other than
this new category of זרעו של אהרן, zaro shel Aharon, but by
מום, they're the same whether it's humans or בהמה, behemah, or קדשים
בכור, whatever, there those specifics are the same, but here you have
a distinctive category of זרעו של אהרן. zaro shel Aharon. Now let's
look at some of the examples. כילון, kilyon,
so what's the
כילון? kilyon? דדמי רישיה לאכלא, d'dami reishei l'achla, his head looks like
a cover of a barrel, which is basically a pointy head. Okay,
so he's basically like a triangle. ליפתא, lifta, which is turnip, דדמי
רישיה לגדגלידה דליפתא, d'dami reishei l'gadgalida d'lifta, like the head of a
turnip, which basically means wide at the top and pointy at the
bottom. תנא, tana, וצוארו עומד באמצע ראשו, v'tzavaro omed b'emtza rosho, also
his neck is like midpoint in the width
of the skull, which means normally your if you think about it,
your neck basically is even at the back of your skull and
it's a little bit inset here. So here the idea is that
the head protrudes, the skull protrudes from the back of the neck
as well. Which is what we're actually מקבן, makaban, Maccabees, there you
go, hammer, hammerhead, דדמי רישיה למקבן, d'dami reishei l'makaban, his head looks
like a hammer, which could mean it protrudes out, it's squarish and
it protrudes out from the front and the back like a hammerhead
shark. שראשו שקוט מלפניו, she'rosho shakut milfanav, שראשו שקוט, she'rosho shakut, what
does שקוט shakut mean? מלפניו, milfanav, it's slanted in the front, וסקיפת,
v'skifat, that the other way, which sticks out a lot? No, it
sounds like Rashi, maybe chin, I thought like Rashi meant the basic
structure of your skull was more like angled rather than flat in
the front, it was more like this angle, וסקיפת מאחוריו, v'skifat me'achorav,
like the back of his head is like somewhat unrounded, it's flattened
and cut off, not literally cut off, but it looks that way,
כי אמרי אינשי, k'amri inshi, like people say, שקיל פיסא, shakil pisa,
so it looks like it's a little bit of
a play on the letters here, פיסא, pisa, שקיל, shakil, like a
piece was removed. It looks like a piece from the back of
the head was removed. תנא, tana, וצוארו שקוט ושמוט. v'tzavaro shakut v'shamut.
So another either this is a clarification of what שקוט shakut means
or it's a variation, his neck is שקוט shakut and שמוט. shamut.
What does this mean? שקוט, shakut, דחזיא מחבא, d'chazya mechaba, it's like
buried,
it's like you have a very short neck and it looks like
your head is like inset between your shoulder blades. שמוט, shamut, דאריך
ושמוט, d'arich v'shamut, which means that your neck is thin and narrow,
so basically it looks more like
the other case, like your head is more protruding
more from both sides of your neck, it's a very thin and
narrow
neck. Okay, so those are all the things with the head. ובעל
חטוטרת, u'ba'al chatoteret, and now people that have a hunchback, a growth
on their back. And Rabbi Yehuda says it's not a problem. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this: דאית ביה עצם כולי עלמא לא
פליגי דפסול. d'it bei etzem kulei alma lo pligi d'pasul. If it
has a bone in it, we had this before by other smaller
skin growths, then everybody agrees it's nobody everybody agrees that it's פסול.
pasul. כי פליגי דלית ביה עצם, ki pligi d'leit bei etzem, there
is no bone. מר סבר, mar savar, הוא אינו שוה בזרעו של
אהרן, hu eino shaveh b'zaro shel Aharon,
again, not quote fair enough to be a מום, but saying that
it's not similar, it's not within the natural normal range of
distribution. ומר סבר, u'mar savar, כקורי דבישרא בעלמא הוא, kakurei d'bishra b'alma
hu, big deal, it's just a piece of it's just like a
piece of flesh.
You're talking about a little thing or is it like it's really?
So I don't know, when you think about hunchback, you think about
the Hunchback of Notre Dame, you think about this huge thing like
a camel, right? Maybe maybe it is more, maybe the guy's standing
up straight and it's just maybe it's big, like it's not huge
like that, but maybe it's not like a tiny pimple, but still,
the guy says okay, so it's a growth of flesh, which again
gets to the question of there are a lot of things that
are אינו שוה בזרעו של אהרן, eino shaveh b'zaro shel Aharon, right?
I mean, what are you going to focus on? I don't know,
hair
color, let's who knows what you're going to focus on? Like a
mole? Right, so exactly, well that maybe actually. So what you have
to do is you first have to decide that this thing is
somehow
problematic. Maybe it's aesthetically problematic, it's not, but this isn't arguing that
it's non-aesthetically problematic, it's just saying what's the big deal? People get
skin growths. But okay, but a lot of these things, what's the
big deal? It's not שוה בזרעו של אהרן. shaveh b'zaro shel Aharon.
So the idea that it's not within the normal range of distribution
is not the only criteria. There's some other criteria here that has
to do like and it matters and it's something of significance. So
one significance is the aesthetics, but here it seems like there's other
things as well because he just says big deal, it's a piece
of flesh.
It's not all aesthetics, if it depends on having a bone or
not having a bone.
That's what I said. The very fact that he said big deal
it's a piece of flesh sounds like he's saying okay, this is
natural. But natural, but does most people have
this? The bone is also natural. Right. How do you measure?
Yeah, very often, you know, these
deformities, if that's what you want to call them, are associated with
other characteristics in the body. So for example, you think of a
Down syndrome person. And so, so they have like, you know, particular
their eyes look something, but they also have other there are other
characteristics which you wouldn't like they're hard to find out. But they
all come kind of as a package. So you know, this is
a person with Down syndrome.
Oh, that's interesting. So you think that the point is that if
we could say that it's just a localized
thing—well, I don't know
if that's what he's saying here, but I'm just pointing out that
that's...
oh, I thought that's what you were saying פשט pshat is about.
So big deal, it's a piece of flesh. Meaning that what he
was saying is okay, so that could be like a totally localized
problem.
Like I know somebody who has... who has kind of a, I
guess you'd call a hunchback. Right. If that were the... you know,
she also has like very kind of long, very slim long limbs.
If it were just the the one thing, then it would be
less... less problematic. Right. So that's...
no, but then, but I thought that you were suggesting that that's
what he was saying. If he was saying okay, it's a bump
of skin, which means maybe this is a highly localized issue and
therefore it we can we can sort of ignore it. It's a
point worth pointing out. Okay, it's interesting. Certainly shows that it's not
just about variation. You have to decide which things matter to be
measuring variation.
What about someone's unusually ugly? No, but things that are...
no. So, but but things that are sort of more quantifiable, yes.
And we'll take a look. Okay, there definitely is an aesthetics going
on. So let's keep on going. I understand, but that's non-quantifiable. Who
are we going to ask? Okay, anyway, let's take a look. הקירח
פסול. Hakireiach pasul. Now how about balding? אמר רבא, Amar Rava, now
there's many different גרסאות girsaot of this גמרא. Gemara לא שנו אלא—we
Lo shanu ela can try reading it with our גרסה—שאין לו לאחוריו
ויש לו לפניו. When is bald problematic? If there's no hair in
the back of the head but there is in the front. Presumably,
yeah presumably that's very strange. It'd be more, more your hair would
fall out in the front and be left some in the back.
So therefore it's like it's very it's very bizarre. אבל יש לו
לאחוריו, Aval yesh lo le-achorav, if you do have a row of
hair in the back even if you don't have in the front,
כשר. kasher. וכל שכן שיש לו לאחוריו ואין לו לפניו. Ve-kol she-ken
she-yesh lo le-achorav ve-ein lo le-fanav. Certainly if you have in the
back and not in the front. Now what do you mean? That's
exactly what he just said, back and not the front. So the
רש״י Rashi has the גרסה girsa כל שכן שאין לו, kol she-ken
she-ein lo, I think he says לא לפניו ולא לאחוריו. lo le-fanav
ve-lo le-achorav. If you have no hair at all, that's completely normal.
Let me just check רש״י. Rashi. No, one minute... אבל יש לו
לפניו כשר וכל שכן שיש לו לאחוריו. Aval yesh lo le-fanav kasher
ve-kol she-ken she-yesh lo le-achorav. No, no, no. רש״י Rashi says if
you have both in front and in back, it's כשר. kasher. Yeah,
both. What? So no, no, it means a row of hair all
the way around and you're bald on the top. That's okay. And
if you're just in the back, you're okay. The only problem would
be if you have in the front and not in the back,
that would be very strange. The basic point here is, while there's
a lot of different גרסאות girsaot and I'm not going to take
you through all of them, is that we're not just saying normal
baldness is a problem, okay? Because of course and some of us
are bald, right? So but we're saying that it's a type of
a baldness that is particularly, you know, bizarre. And he says that's
צרעת tzara'at baldness. No, that has that requires a נתק. netek. No,
I know, but I'm saying the... could be. Yeah, but not that
by itself. ואיכא דמתני אסיפא. Ve-ika de-matni a-seifa. Some say that רבא's
Rava's point was not going on the רישא reisha where it says
it is a problem, but if it on the סיפא seifa where
it says when it's not a problem when it has a row
all around the head. ואם יש לו הרי זה כשר. Ve-im yesh
lo harei zeh kasher. If there is a row around, it's כשר.
kasher. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, לא שנו אלא שיש לו לאחוריו lo
shanu ela she-yesh lo le-achorav and ואין לו לפניו.
ve-ein lo le-fanav. That's okay.
אבל יש לו בין לאחוריו בין לפניו פסול. Aval yesh lo bein
le-achorav bein le-fanav pasul. But if it has...
it should really be...
both, not בין bein again, it's a strange גרסה. girsa But the
way רש״י Rashi reads it is, if it has one row all
the way around, that's פסול, pasul, because that's very bizarre. You know,
a guy has a row all the way around at the base
and it's totally bald in the middle, that's very bizarre. That's פסול.
pasul. וכל שכן שיש לו לפניו ואין לו לאחוריו, Ve-kol she-ken she-yesh
lo le-fanav ve-ein lo le-achorav, and also if it has only in
the front and not in the back. So anyway, the גרסאות girsaot
here are a little bit of a question, but the point you
get is that if it's a type of a natural appearance of
balding it's not a problem. Also תוספות Tosafot has the גרסה girsa.
כל שכן kol she-ken if he's totally bald it's not a problem.
Or not תוספות, Tosafot, the שיטה מקובצת. Shita Mekubetzet. Okay, so it's
only a type of a baldness that is very strange and that
looks very weird. Okay, ודאין לו... U-de-ein lo... oh, our גרסה girsa
is, excuse me, ודאין לו כלל דפסול. u-de-ein lo klal de-pasul. If
you don't have at all it's פסול. pasul. But I believe the
שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet has, let me see... yeah, the שיטה מקובצת
Shita Mekubetzet has one גרסה girsa on ו, Vav, he says אבל
אין לו כלל כשר aval ein lo klal kasher by the first
לשון lashon of רבא. Rava. The second לשון lashon of רבא Rava
would say אין לו כלל פסול. ein lo klal pasul. Now see,
that's really interesting. I know, that's my point. So that normal types
of appearances of baldness are not a problem, only ones that are
very strange. No, according to the other גרסה girsa you just said,
the שיטה מקובצת, Shita Mekubetzet, then it is פסול pasul if he's
totally bald. Yeah, and that's what our גרסה girsa is, and I
think even in the second לשון lashon of רבא. Rava. that not
at all is פסול *pasul*, okay? But anyway, things that are normally
natural, I don’t know, how common is it for somebody bald to
have absolutely no hair? Don’t even balding people usually have some hair
in the back? I mean
I know you have the
whole Yul Brynner look but whatever. Right, but otherwise you almost always
have some hair in the back, right? So it’s very hard, you
know, unless it’s really quite a rare bizarre case to have that.
What? Maybe you know natural well standard baldness you know it’s it
varies from a little bit to a lot but there’s still some
hair left but there are
kinds which are so unusual which you might classify more as outside
the norm. Right.
So that I think is what’s being said here, exactly, that normal
baldness is not a problem, only things that are very rare. Yes,
let’s just say there’s a sign of צרעת *tzara'as*... צרעת *tzara'as*, in
פרשת תזריע *Parshat Tazria* it mentions בבהק *bebahak* or something in this
spot. Correct, right. Right, but that’s when it comes with a צרעת
*tzara'as*, not just baldness per se. That’s what I meant. Alright, let’s
keep on going. So now it says like this, אמר רבי יוחנן
*Amar Rabbi Yochanan*, הקרחנים והננסים *Harkarchanim Vehananasim*, the bald people, and as
we said it’s a very strange form of baldness, not a normal
baldness, והננסים *vehananasim* midgets, okay, is that the, is that the PC
term?
Is there a PC term? Dwarfs, dwarfs, is the PC term... whatever,
for some people. Alright anyway, והסבלגנין *vehasavleganin*, and סבלגנין *savleganim* which basically
means people that have, you know, tearing eyes as a permanent condition.
So פסולים *psulim*, are פסול *pasul* לפי שאינו שוה בזרעו של אהרן
*lefi she'eino shaveh bezaro shel Aharon*.
Again, not because they're מום *mum*, these are not מום *mum*, that’s
interesting right? Even a midget or whatever it’s not a מום *mum*,
it’s just totally
outside the normal range but it’s not like a physical blemish as
we’ve been defining
a מום *mum*, but these are, but it’s not
שוה בזרעו של אהרן *shaveh bezaro shel Aharon*.
So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, קרחנים
תנינא *Karchanim tanina*, what do you mean? These are all in the
משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*, who needs רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* to tell this
to us? קרח *Kereach* is in our משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah*, ננסים תנינא
*Nanasim tanina*, the midgets is in a משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* that’s coming
up. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, סבלגנין אצטריכא ליה *Savleganim itzricha lei*,
no, it needs the case of watery eyes, that’s not in the
משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah*. לאשמועינן *Le'ashmi'unan*, to tell us. ומה דתימא *Uma detema*,
I might have thought משום מראית העין *mishum mar'is ha'ayin*, that even
though that these types of things are problem... one minute... oh yes,
that number one
סבלגנין *savleganim* is not
mentioned
in the משנה *Mishnah*, the watery eyes. Number two, even though these
other things קרח *kereach* and whatever are mentioned in the משנה *Mishnah*,
I have to know why, in what category they fall, right? Because
we’ve now defined three categories: מום *mum*, אינו שוה בזרעו של אהרן
*eino shaveh bezaro shel Aharon*, and מראית העין *mar'is ha'ayin*, and there’s
a big halakhic difference. So part of what רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*
is teaching me is not only that they’re in the משנה *Mishnah*,
that I know, but that they’re in this middle category of אינו
שוה בזרעו של אהרן *eino shaveh bezaro shel Aharon*. But מראית העין
*mar'is ha'ayin* is actually better, it’s right, it’s less of a הלכה
*halakhah* problem. Right. So it says like this, where were we? לאשמועינן
*Le'ashmi'unan*, and it’s to teach me... סבלגנין אצטריכא ליה לאשמועינן ומה דתימא
משום מראית העין *Savleganim itzricha lei le'ashmi'unan uma detema mishum mar'is ha'ayin*,
that these are problems only because of the visuals and they’re not
even the זרעו של אהרן zaro shel Aharon. *zaro shel Aharon* problem.
So therefore he’s telling me that they’re in the זרעו של אהרן
zaro shel Aharon *zaro shel Aharon* problem. So the גמרא *Gemara* says
one minute, וכל היכא דאיכא משום מראית העין תני קתני *vechal heicha
de'ika mishum mar'is ha'ayin tani kataney*, ושנשרו ריסי עיניו פסול מפני מראית
העין *veshnishru risei eyney pasul mipnei mar'is ha'ayin*. How can you claim
that the problem is because of מראית העין *mar'is ha'ayin*? It tells
you explicitly that it’s only a מראית העין *mar'is ha'ayin* problem. קתני
ושנשרו ריסי עיניו פסול מפני מראית העין *Kataney veshnishru risei eyney pasul
mipnei mar'is ha'ayin*. When, for example, when it says that your eyelashes
fell off, the משנה *Mishnah* says explicitly מראית העין *mar'is ha'ayin*. So
it’s saying who needs רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* to teach me it’s
not a מראית העין *mar'is ha'ayin* issue? When it is only מראית
העין *mar'is ha'ayin*, the משנה *Mishnah* labels it that explicitly. So you
could have still thought that he was teaching me it’s not a
מום *mum*, but that’s interesting, the גמרא *Gemara* takes
for obvious it’s not a מום *mum*.
These aren’t physical blemishes, it’s not like a... you know, like a
physical thing on the body, hair fell out, you know, guy is
born a dwarf, that’s not a מום *mum*, that’s interesting, the גמרא
*Gemara* takes that for granted. So the only thing that רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan* has to teach me is it’s not מראית העין *mar'is
ha'ayin*. Says well that also I can figure out, because whenever it’s
מראית העין *mar'is ha'ayin* the משנה *Mishnah* says it explicitly. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says no, ומה דתימא *uma detema*, I might have thought
תני חדא והוא הדין לכולהו *tani chada vehu hadin lechulhu*. When it
says משום מראית העין *mishum mar'is ha'ayin* that’s on the last case
but it actually refers to all of the previous cases as well.
So therefore he had to tell me, he had to tell me
not, meaning what we’re going to see is, right? There’s always a
question in the משניות *Mishnayot* how do you punctuate? A משנה *Mishnah*
says here are the things that are מום *mum* for כהנים koanim,
*Kohanim*, and it mentions all these types of things about the funny
shaped heads and about the hunchback and about the baldness, and then
the next משנה *Mishnah* you keep on reading and then one משנה
*Mishnah* says ta-da-da-da-da-da משום מראית העין *mishum mar'is ha'ayin*. So the question
is what’s משום מראית העין *mishum mar'is ha'ayin* going on? Is it
going on the immediately last mentioned thing which is the eyelashes, or
is it going on like the whole list of the last 20
things? Who knows where to draw the line? So yes, רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan* had to tell it to me, that he had to
tell me that it’s not מראית העין *mar'is ha'ayin*. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says one minute, וכל היכא דאיכא מהדר מתני *vechal heicha de'ika
mahadar misni*, so every time... that would be okay if it only
said מראית העין *mar'is ha'ayin* once, but it says מראית העין *mar'is
ha'ayin* in the משנה *Mishnah* more than once. So if every time
it repeats, it says מראית העין *mar'is ha'ayin* more than once, it
means that only the things that are singled out are the מראית
עין mar'is ayin problems, right? Because if they were a problem of
the whole list, it wouldn't have to say it more than once.
קהדר ותני Kahadar v'tanei because we go again and we teach, בשניטלו
שיניו v'shenitlu shinav if his teeth fell out, פסול משום מראית העין.
pasul mishum mar'is ha'ayin. So you see when it says, we assume
it's a non-מראית עין mar'is ayin, problem unless it is singled out
as such. And also the גמרא say we take for granted that
these things are not a מום. So if they're not a מום
and the משנה did not single them out as מראית עין, mar'is
ayin so of course they're because of זרעו של אהרן. zaro shel
Aharon, What is ר' יוחנן Reb Yochanan teaching us? So the גמרא
says אלא לאפוקי מהא דתניא, ela l'afokei me'ha d'tanya, you're right. He's
not teaching me a new idea, but he's פסקנ'ינג paskening for us
because there's a ברייתא Baraisa that it's under debate. דתניא, D'tanya, we
taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa, הכרחנים והננסים והזבלגנין, hakarchanim v'hananasim v'hazavlaganim, these
three categories כשרים ksherim are actually כשר. kasher. ולא אמרו פסול אלא
מפני מראית העין. v'lo amru pasul ela mipnei mar'is ha'ayin. So actually
there's a ברייתא Baraisa that actually says these are just a מראית
עין mar'is ayin problem. These are not a זרעו של אהרן zaro
shel Aharon. problem. That's not our משנה. Our משנה, as we argued,
would make it a זרעו של אהרן, zaro shel Aharon but it
is the ברייתא. Baraisa. מאן האי תנא, Man hai tana, and who
is this תנא? tana? ר' יהודה. Rebi Yehuda. דתניא ר' יהודה אומר,
D'tanya Rebi Yehuda omer, הכהנים hakoanim לרבות הכרחנים. l'rabos hakarchanim. It says
these are the כהנים koanim to tell me that even bald כהנים,
somehow he gets it from this extra word, I don't know how,
are כשר. kasher. So if there's a problem, it is only a
מראית עין mar'is ayin, problem. So what the גמרא has now done
is, it has actually again been consistent with these three categories and
actually pointed out a natural ambiguity in our משנה. We're assuming basically
everything listed that the כהנים are more than בהמה beheimah is not
a מום, but it's a זרעו של אהרן. zaro shel Aharon Now
where you draw the line between זרעו של אהרן and מראית עין,
mar'is ayin, when it says מראית עין, mar'is ayin how much of
the list does it apply to? And the גמרא says since it's
repeated, it only applies to the ones that are immediately juxtaposed, the
ones like that immediately precede it. And only those that are singled
out are limited to a minimum מראית עין problem; everything else is
this זרעו של אהרן problem. So we will continue with this.